Register of the Stephen Miles Bouton Papers, 1918-1962
Hoover Institution Archives
Stephen Miles Bouton Papers
1918-1962
83014
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (2.5 linear feet)
Memoirs, dispatches, newspaper columns, other writings, speeches, and correspondence, relating to the German revolution of 1918, German politics and society from World War I to World War II, interwar European politics, and social conditions and civil liberties in the U.S.
Bouton, Stephen Miles, 1876-
Biographical Note
1876, September 24 Born, Blockville, N.Y.
1899 LL.B., Albany Law School Admitted to N.Y. bar; practiced at Jamestown, N.Y.
1903, November 11 Married Frieda Dorothea Kleinsang
1903-1904 On staff, Meadville (Pa.) Star
1904-1905 On staff, Oil City Times
1905-1909 On staff, Buffalo Express
1909-1919 With Associated Press
1911 Transferred to Berlin, Germany
1911-1912, 1925-1927 Studied, University of Berlin
1914-1916 With the German army on various fronts as war correspondent
1916-1919 In charge of Associated Press bureau in Stockholm, Sweden
1917, Summer In Petrograd
1918, November First enemy correspondent to enter Berlin after the armistice
1920 Author, And the Kaiser Abdicates
1920-1934 Berlin correspondent, N.Y. World, N.Y. Times, Baltimore Sun
1922 Author, Das Ende der Grossmacht Deutschland
1934, June Ordered by the Hitler government to leave Germany
1935-1939 Lecturer
1940's-1950's Chief editorial writer, The Post-Journal, Jamestown, N.Y.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
Memoirs, dispatches, newspaper columns, other writings, speeches, and correspondence, relating to the German revolution of 1918, German politics and society from World War I to World War II, interwar European politics, and social conditions and civil liberties in the U.S.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Civil rights--United States.; Europe--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Europe.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.; Germany--Politics and government--20th century.; Germany--Social conditions.; Germany.; Journalists.; United States--Social conditions.; United States.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1962. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Unidentified, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander-Ferdinand, Prince of Prussia, 1929 (Folder 2)
  - Bernstorff, 1923-1925 (Folder 3)
  - Bouton, Johnny, 1955 (Folder 4)
  - Burlingame, Roger, 1938 (Folder 5)
  - Eckener, Hugo, 1934 (Folder 6)
  - Goodell, Charles E., 1942 (Folder 7)
  - Haeckel, Ernst, 1919 (Folder 8)
  - Keating, Kenneth B., 1962 (Folder 9)
  - Lamont, Corliss, 1960 (Folder 10)
  - Lewis, Sinclair, 1926-1934 (Folder 11)
  - Lowell, Stanley, 1962 (Folder 12)
  - Ludendorff, General Erich (Folder 13)
  - Mahoney, Joseph C., 1957 (Folder 14)
  - Mencken, H. L., 1936-1946 (Folder 15)
  - Rieckent(?), J., 1955 (Folder 16)
  - Seymour, H. T., 1960 (Folder 17)
  - Stresemann, Gustav, 1925-1928 (Folder 18)
  - Sudermann, Hermann, 1923 (Folder 19)
  - U.S. Department of State, 1918-1920 (Folder 20)
  - Wagner, Winifred, 1923 (Folder 21)
  - Wilhelm, Prince, 1927-1939 (Folder 22)
- JOURNALISM CAREER FILE, 1918-1959. (Box 1-4)
  Articles, dispatches, newspaper columns, and notes by S. M. Bouton, arranged chronologically.
  - Notes on Berlin, Typescript, holograph, and mimeographed copies, November 1918-March 1919. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Articles and dispatches, mostly for the Baltimore Sun and the Washington Post, on Germany. Typescript, printed, and carbon copies (Folder 24)
    - 1920-1933
    - 1933-1939 (Folder 25)
  - Dispatches from Danzig, Prague, Warsaw, Vienna, and Paris, Typescript and carbon copies, 1920's-1930's. (Folder 26)
  - Articles, essays, interviews, as well as newspaper columns for the Post-Journal entitled Of Many Things, on the United States (Folder 27)
    - Typescript, printed, and carbon copies, 1925-1935.
    - Printed copies (pasted on loose cardboard sheets), 1941-1945. (Box 2-3)
    - Typescript and carbon copies, 1949-1957. (Box 3)
    - Printed copies, 1950-1951. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Printed copies, 1958-1959. (Folder 2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1931-1962. (Box 4-6)
  Articles, conference papers, essays, lectures, letters to the editor, manuscripts of books, memoirs, and notes by S. M. Bouton, arranged chronologically.
  - The Double Patriot, Carbon copy short story, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fake Relics and Miracles, Printed article (Folder 4)
  - Interview of General Erich Ludendorff, Typescript copy, with holograph annotations by General Ludendorff (Folder 5)
  - An Irregular Adoption, Typescript short story, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - And the Kaiser Abdicates, Printed review, New York Times Book Review and Magazine, 1920. January 2, 1921 (Folder 7)
  - Chiefly Concerning Garet Garret, June 1923.; Pamphlet (Folder 8)
  - Lectures, American Women's Club of Berlin, Typescript notes, April 1931-January 1932. (Folder 9)
  - Speeches, Svenska Föreningen, Berlin (Swedish Club). Typescript transcripts (Folder 10)
    - In Swedish, 1933, November 11.
    - In German, 1934, April 14. (Folder 11)
  - Memoir re Sinclair Lewis, Typescript account of an incident that took place in 1928, which throws a special light on the man's kindness of heart..., c. 1934. (Folder 12)
  - Article re Adolf Hitler, Printed copy., June 18, 1934. (Folder 13)
    Includes material related to the controversy between Archbishop Michael J. Curley and the Baltimore Sun surrounding the article, in which S. M. Bouton compares Hitler to Ignatius Loyola
  - Yugoslavia and the Present Balance of Power in the Balkans, Typescript essay, c. 1935. (Folder 14)
  - My Years in Germany. Reprint from the Proceedings of the Institute of Public Affairs, Ninth Annual Session, The University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, January 23-30, 1935 (Folder 15)
  - The Totalitarian State. Reprint from the Proceedings of the Institute of Public Affairs, Ninth Annual Session, The University of Georgia, Athens, Georgia, January 23-30, 1935 (Folder 16)
  - Hitlerism Menaces European Peace. Printed account of a speech delivered before the Rockford Woman's Club, Rockford, Ill., March 27, 1935 (Folder 17)
  - Lectures, Columbia University, Typescript notes, 1937. (Folder 18)
  - Germany Goes German, Manuscript of a book never published, 1937. (Folder 19)
    - Carbon copy
    - Typescript copy (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Article re European federation, Mimeographed copy, 1940. (Folder 2)
  - Fritz Reuter, Typescript and printed copies, 1947. (Folder 3)
  - Autobiographical notes, Holograph, 1955. (Folder 4)
  - Letters to the editor, relating to the fall of the Weimar Republic and to separation of church and state in the United States, 1957-1962 (Folder 5)
  - America's Place among the Nations. Carbon copy of a paper delivered before the University Club (of Jamestown, N.Y.?), October 2, 1958 (Folder 6)
  - Religion in American Politics. Mimeographed copy of a paper delivered before the University Club of Jamestown, N.Y., December 1, 1960 (Folder 7)
  - A Veteran Journalist Reports, Manuscript of memoirs never published, c. 1962. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Carbon copy
    - Typescript copy (Folder 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1932-1956. (Box 6)
  Articles by others and related correspondence by S. M. Bouton, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Academics in the United States (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Censorship in the arts (Folder 4)
  - Separation of church and state (Folder 5)
  - Völkischer Beobachter. Includes correspondence of S. M. Bouton and Louis Lochner - both misrepresented in a photograph caption - with the editor, 1932 (Folder 6)
- MISCELLANY FILE, n.d. n.d. (Box 6)
  Poem and invitation card.
  - Invitation to a beer evening sent out by S. M. Bouton while in Germany. Printed card, in English and German (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Poem by Noel L. Bouton, brother of S. M. Bouton. Carbon copy, in a German dialect (Folder 8)
- PHOTOGRAPHS AND POSTCARDS, c. 1910's-1950's. (Box 10. A-V)
  2 prints and 1 postcard depicting S.M. Bouton, circa 1910s-1950s; and 1 postcard, autographed, depicting Count Luckner, German U-boat captain and explorer, 1926.